<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Articles ecclesiastical to be enquired of by the church-wardens and sworne-men within the [blank] in the visitation of the [blank] and in the ([blank] yeere of the reigne of our most dread soueraigne lord King Iames)</title>
            <author>Church of England.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1621</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 24 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A00136</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 10133.9</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S421</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">22370601</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 22370601</idno>
            <idno type="VID">25480</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A00136)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 25480)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1752:57)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Articles ecclesiastical to be enquired of by the church-wardens and sworne-men within the [blank] in the visitation of the [blank] and in the ([blank] yeere of the reigne of our most dread soueraigne lord King Iames)</title>
                  <author>Church of England.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[13] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn Bill,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1621.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴(-A1) B⁴.</note>
                  <note>Formerly STC 10219.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Visitations, Ecclesiastical --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:25480:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>ARTICLES ECCLESIASTICAL TO be enquired of by the Church-wardens and Sworne-men with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <p>In the Viſitation of the <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And in the <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> yeere of the Reigne of our most dread Soueraigne Lord King</hi> IAMES.</p>
            <p>LONDON Printed by IOHN BILL. 1621.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="oath">
            <pb facs="tcp:25480:2"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> The Oath.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Ou ſhall ſweare by the Name of Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty God, well and truely to execute the Office of Churchwardens and Sidemen, &amp;c. That you ſhall diligently conſider, and enquire of all and euery the Articles following, and make a true anſwere to euery of the ſame ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally, and diſtinctly in writing, preſenting euery perſon of your Pariſh, who hath, or ſhall, in your Pariſh, or elſewhere: and euery perſon of any other Pariſh, who hath, or ſhall in your Pariſh commit any offence or fault, mentioned in any of the ſaid Articles, or which are pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely, and credibly defamed for any ſuch offence, or fault: wherein you ſhall not vnduely preſent any perſon or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of euill will, malice, or any corrupt affection, nor ſhall for loue, fauour, dread, or any other indirect affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, ſpare to preſent any that bee offenders in any of thoſe caſes, but ſhall doe vprightly, as men hauing the feare of God before your eyes, and deſirous to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine vertue, and ſuppreſſe vice. So helpe you God by Chriſt Ieſus.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="articles">
            <pb facs="tcp:25480:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>¶ Note, you are by your ſaid Oath to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent truely what you either know of your owne knowledge, or what is publikely or credibly famed and ſpoken touching any matter or thing contained in any Article following.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Irſt, whether any perſon whatſoeuer of your Pariſh doth maintaine or defend any Hereſies, falſe opinions, or Popiſh errors, contrary to the word of God, and the Articles of Religion eſtabliſhed in this Realme?</p>
            <p n="2">2 Whether any perſon bee an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugner or deprauer either in word or writing the of forme of Eccleſiaſticall gouernement of the Church of England, or of the Booke of Common prayer, or the Rites and Ceremonies preſcribed therein, or of the Kings ſupremacie in cauſes Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall, or of the Oath of Supremacie or Allegeance?</p>
            <p n="3">3 Whether any Parſon doth reade publique Seruice in any Church or Chappell, not beeing lawfully ordered Deacon at the leaſt, and licenſed by the Lord Biſhop or his Chauncellor.</p>
            <p n="4">4 Whether any Parſon, Vicar, or Curate preſume to preach in their Cures, or elſewhere, not being licenced by the Biſhop or Ordinarie?</p>
            <p n="5">5 Whether is your Parſon or Vicar knowen, or probably
<pb facs="tcp:25480:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
and publikely famed or reported to haue obtained his Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice by Simony, or to let out his Liuing to farme, or any part thereof to any perſon in conſideration of any ſuch Simonia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call compact.</p>
            <p n="6">6 Whether haue you had a Sermon preached euery Sabbath day this laſt yeere in your Church: if not, yet how many haue you had? and vpon thoſe Sundaies that you had not a Sermon, haue you had an Homely read?</p>
            <p n="7">7 Whether hath any ſtranger been ſuffered to preach in your Church or Chappell, without hauing firſt ſhewed his licence to preach vnto the Miniſter and Churchwardens ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the 50. Canon.</p>
            <p n="8">8 Whether doth your Miniſter vpon euery Sunday and Holy day in the afternoone before euening prayer call for, and inſtruct all the youth and ignorant perſons of your Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, of both Sexes, in the Catechiſme, and grounds of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion for halfe an houre or more?</p>
            <p n="9">9 Whether bee there any Parents, Maſters, or gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, who ſend not their children, or ſeruants to bee chate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chized on euery Sabbath day, and Holy day, or any children or ſeruants that refuſe to bee inſtructed or examined?</p>
            <p n="10">10 Whether doth your Miniſter neglect or forſake his calling, and betake himſelfe to worldly affaires, mercenary, or manuell Trades, haunt markets, or intermeddle with, or ſolicite matters of Law for other men?</p>
            <p n="11">11 Whether doth your Miniſter haunt or frequent Ale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſes, or Tauernes, or is hee probably or publikely famed or any notorious crime, or any euill example of life, to the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence and ſcandall of his vocation?</p>
            <p n="12">12 Whether doth your Miniſter vſe or weare any kind of apparell which is vnſeeming his calling, for colour or faſhion of the ſame, or otherwiſe then according to the 74. Canon?</p>
            <p n="13">13 Whether doeth your Miniſter at all times weare the Surpleſſe in the time of Diuine Seruice and adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Sacraments? And if hee bee a Graduate, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doeth hee alſo vpon his Surpleſſe weare a hood incident to his degree?</p>
            <p n="14">
               <pb facs="tcp:25480:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>14 Whether doe you know, or haue credibly and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely heard of any within your Pariſh that are procurers of Schiſmes, or maintainers of Schiſmatikes, or which are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorters to conuenticles, or congregations of the Kings Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects, other then ſuch as by the Lawes Eccleſiaſticall of this Realme are allowed?</p>
            <p n="15">15 Whether doeth your Miniſter vſe any other forme of Common prayer, then is preſcribed in the Booke of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon prayer, and whether doth hee vſe ſuch directions, rites, and ceremonies in Seruice, and the adminiſtration of the Sacraments, as by the ſaid booke are required, and none other?</p>
            <p n="16">16 Whether doeth your miniſter admit to the Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion any notorious adulterer fornicator, or inceſtuous per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, or other great offender which hath not firſt done his penance, or any ſtranger of another Pariſh, contrary to the 28. Canon?</p>
            <p n="17">17 Whether haue any been married within your Pariſh that haue not vpon the day of their marriage receiued the holy Communion? or any been married in times prohibited, or without banes ſolemnely aſked three ſeuerall Sundayes, otherwiſe then by licence of the Ordinary, as you know, or credibly and publikely haue heard?</p>
            <p n="18">18 Whether hath your Miniſter vſed the forme of thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuing preſcribed for women after childbirth, for any woman vnlawfully begotten with childe, otherwiſe then in the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bite of a penitent ſinner, or before ſufficient caution be taken for her not departing the Pariſh vntill ſhee hath done penance for her offence?</p>
            <p n="19">19 Whether doth your Parſon, Preacher, Lecturer, and Vicar in his owne perſon, at the leaſtwiſe in euery yeere vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on two Sundayes publikely, both in the forenoone and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noone in your Church or Chappell, reade Diuine Seruice, and adminiſter both the Sacraments in ſuch manner and forme as is preſcribed by the Booke of Common prayer ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the 56. Canon?</p>
            <p n="20">20 Whether doth your Miniſter dayly viſite the ſicke,
<pb facs="tcp:25480:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
and exhort them truely to beleeue in Chriſt, and repent ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of their ſinnes, and comfort and pray for them, as is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed in the Booke of Common prayer?</p>
            <p n="21">21 Whether doth your Parſon, Vicar, or Farmor of the Tithes, ſuffer either the Parſonage or Vicarage-houſe or other buildings thereto belonging, or the Chancell to fall to ruine or decay, and doth not preſently repaire them?</p>
            <p n="22">22 Whether hath any perſon taken away or vncouered a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Church, Chappell or Chancell, or any part of them, or any Church porch, or Veſtrie, or hath pulled downe the belles, or made any other ſpoile or waſte vpon his Benefice, either in timber, or woods?</p>
            <p n="23">23 Whether is your Church euery way ſufficiently, and well repayred, and no defect in glazing, tiling, ſieling, pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, or in any thing elſe belonging to the ſame: and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Church bee beautified, and adorned with Scripture ſentences?</p>
            <p n="24">24 Whether is your Church-yard ſufficiently fenced with Wall, Raile, Pale or other fence, and is your Church-yard profaned, or ſwine ſuffered to roote there?</p>
            <p n="25">25 Whether haue you in your Pariſh Church or Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell the new booke of Common prayer, two Pſalters, the Bible in Engliſh of the largeſt volume, lately ſet foorth by his Maieſties authoritie, the two volumes of Homilies, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Iewels</hi> workes, <hi>Eraſmus</hi> Paraphraſe, the table of the tenne Commandements, and the Table of the degrees of Affinitie and Conſanguinitie, wholly and vntorne, a conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient Pulpit, a fit ſeate for your Miniſter, a decent Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion Table vpon a frame, a linnen cloth to couer it, with ſome other couer of ſilke, or ſuch like, a Communion cuppe of ſiluer, and couer of the ſame, a cleane ſweete ſtanding Pet, or ſtoope of pewter, or other purer mettall, to put in the wine for the vſe of the Communion, a ſufficient fou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> well couered, decent Surpleſſe of fine holland, with large ſleeues, a ſure coffer with three lockes for the Regiſter Booke, a ſtrong cheſt with three lockes there to for the almeſboxe, and haue your Miniſter and Churchwardens ſeuerall keyes to thoſe
<pb facs="tcp:25480:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Coffers according to the 70. Canon?</p>
            <p n="26">26 Whether doth your Miniſter and Churchwardens euery Sunday after Euening prayer take the Regiſter booke, and then Regiſter the names of all thoſe who were Chriſtned, married or buried the weeke before, and is the ſame a faire booke of parchment, and ſafely kept vnder lockes and keyes?</p>
            <p n="27">27 Whether doth any Parſon ſerue two Cures, or any Curate ſerue his Cure not in due time? and what ſlipend hath your Curate by the yeare?</p>
            <p n="28">28 Whether hath your Miniſter publiſhed and executes all ſuch proceſſes, excommunications, and penances as haue been directed vnto him from the Lord Biſhop or his Chancellour, in ſuch ſort as was preſcribed and without delay? and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath he duly made Certificates thereof, and of all penan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces according as they haue beene performed and no otherwiſe, as you know, or credibly and publiquely haue heard?</p>
            <p n="29">29 Whether hath your Parſon or Vicar moe Benefices then one, how many, and in what places be they? what be the names, and values of them, and whether is he abſent from among you aboue 80. dayes in all in any one yeare? and if hee hath two Benefices, hath he a preaching Curate on that Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefice whereon he doth not reſide? and whether doth he let any leaſe of any of his Benefices, or any part thereof? and to whom? and for how long?</p>
            <p n="30">30 Whether is your Clarke aged twenty yeares at leaſt, and approued by the Ordinary, and hath hee taken an Oath, and is he able to read diſtinctly, as by law is required, and is he diligent in keeping the Church, Chauncell, Communion table, Font, Bookes, ornaments of the Church, and all ſuch things as belong to his charge ſafe, decent and cleane?</p>
            <p n="31">31 Whether is there any Schoolemaſter teaching either openly or priuately in your Pariſh, or any perſon who practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth Phiſick, or Surgerie? and what be their names?</p>
            <p n="32">32 Whether haue any Lords of Miſrule, Dauncers, Play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, or any other diſguiſed perſons beene ſuffered to enter the Church, Chappell, or Churchyard with their ſports? and if they haue, what be the names of ſuch diſordered perſons?</p>
            <p n="33">
               <pb facs="tcp:25480:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>33 Whether be there in your Pariſh any vnlawfull exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes vſed vpon any Sabaoth, or Feſtiuall dayes? whether doe any vſe dauncing or ſuch like ſports on the Sabaoth day before the end of all diuine Seruice appointed for that day? whether be there any common drinking in your Church? who were preſent at ſuch drinking, or ſports, and whether any doe ſit in the Tauerne, Alehouſe, or Streete vpon Sundayes or Holy-dayes in the time of morning or euening prayer?</p>
            <p n="34">34 Whether be there any in your Pariſh that vſe any han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die craft, or worke, or keepe open ſhop vpon any Sabbaoth or Feſtiuall day, or that within time of Harueſt doe vpon Holy-dayes labour about their Harueſt, or then vſe any carriages by Wayne, or otherwiſe, vnleſſe neceſſity ſhall require, or the law permit it?</p>
            <p n="35">35 Whether there be in your Pariſh any diſturbers of the diuine ſeruice of God, or which doe vſe any talking, walking, or any vnreuerent behauiour in Church or Churchyard in time of diuine ſeruice?</p>
            <p n="36">36 Whether doth your Miniſter giue warning afore-hand to his Pariſhioners for the receiuing of the Communion, and are there any in your Pariſh of conuenient age, <hi>viz.</hi> aboue ſix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teene yeares, that doe not receiue the Communion thrice in euery yeare at the leaſt? or any that receiue the Communion otherwiſe then moſt reuerently kneeling on their knees?</p>
            <p n="37">37 Whether any of your Pariſh doe receiue Seminarie Prieſts or other Seducers into their houſes, and whether there be any Strangers that ſocourne in your Pariſh, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally about Eaſter, and doe abſent themſelues from Church?</p>
            <p n="38">38 Whether haue your Churchwardens beene diligent themſelues in frequenting diuine ſeruice, and doing their of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice? and duly giuen account at the yeares end of the goods, and rents of the Church, or not diſtributed the publique almes indifferently?</p>
            <p n="39">39 Whether when any man or woman is paſſing out of this life, the Bell be tolled to giue warning to the people to pray for the ſicke perſon? if not, in whoſe default.</p>
            <p n="40">40 Whether any perſon of your Pariſh hath remained ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicate
<pb facs="tcp:25480:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
by the ſpace of fourty dayes? and whether any excommunicate perſon hath intruded himſelfe or beene admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto diuine ſeruice, the Sacrament or like publique aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies? and who are keepers of company with any excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate perſon, or doe harbour any excommunicate perſon in their houſes, or ſet them to worke contrary to the law?</p>
            <p n="41">41 Whether any excommunicate Recuſant, or other ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate excommunicants haue beene buried in your Church, or Churchyard? by whom were they ſo buried? and who were preſent?</p>
            <p n="42">42 Whether any of your Pariſh be knowne, or credibly and publiquely famed to be attempters of the chaſtity of any woman, or inceſtuous perſons, or adulterers, or fornicatours before or after marriage? Bawdes or receptors of incontinent perſons into their houſes, or which conuay them away before they haue done penance for the ſame? and whether any that heretofore haue for thoſe crimes departed your Pariſh vnpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, are now returned againe?</p>
            <p n="43">43 Whether there be any blaſphemers of the name of God, or ſwearers, or any common drunkards, ſlaunderers or defa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers of their neighbours in your Pariſh? and what are their names?</p>
            <p n="44">44 Whether any perſon in your Pariſh be knowne or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted to vſe any Witchcraft, Sorcerie, Charmes, or any that doe take vpon them to tell deſtinies, or to guide men to things loſt, or any that reſorteth vnto ſuch for helpe and counſell?</p>
            <p n="45">45 Whether haue there beene any children borne in your Pariſh, which haue not beene brought to be baptized in your Pariſh Church? (and whether any children of your Pariſh haue been baptized by a Seminarie Prieſt? what is the name of that Prieſt? and whether any of the children of Recuſants or Soiourners with Recuſants haue had their baptiſme de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred longer then the next Sabboth day, or which remaine as yet vnbaptized? and whoſe are thoſe children?)</p>
            <p n="46">46 Whether hath any Father anſwered as Godfather to his owne childe, and whether haue any beene admitted to be Godfather or Godmother to any childe in your Pariſh, who
<pb facs="tcp:25480:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
before that time haue not receiued the holy Communion?</p>
            <p n="47">47 Whether any perſons of your Pariſh diuorced lawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, doe notwithſtanding accompany together? and whether any perſons lawfully married, haue forſaken their wiues or huſbands, or liue not together, or any which haue married any perſon contracted to others, or which had not the conſent of their parents? and whether any were married in any priuate houſe, or within the degrees prohibited, or not betweene the houres of eight and twelue of the clocke in the forenoone?</p>
            <p n="48">48 Whether doe you know any perſon formerly preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, which hath not beene conuented and cenſured by the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie for the ſame? or any enioyned to doe pennance, who ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath not done it, or done it not penitently, but ſcornfully, and not in forme, habite, and time preſcribed, or any that haue laughed or ſcorned at thoſe, who haue done their pennance? and what be their names?</p>
            <p n="49">49 Whether any Hoſpitall or Almes-houſe be either pulled downe or growne to decay? whether the number of poore and impotent perſons appointed by the founders are maintained there? and if not, in whoſe default? whether any lands or lega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies giuen to ſuch or other godly vſes, are not imployed accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly? and whether any rights, or duties belonging to your Church be detained by any perſon?</p>
            <p n="50">50 Whether doe you know any perſon within your Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, who directly or indirectly taketh vſurie or intereſt for mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney lent, contrary to the lawes of God and this Realme? who are they? and what is the manner of their vſurie?</p>
            <p n="51">51 Whether any perſon of your Pariſh hath ſuppreſſed the laſt will and teſtament of any perſon deceaſed, or adminiſtred the goods of any perſon inteſtate before adminiſtration com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted vnto him? whether doe you know any forgers or chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers of ſuch will? or any Executor which hath not fulfilled the Teſtators will in payment of Legacies to good and godly vſes?</p>
            <p n="52">52 Whether haue your Churchwardens ſolde or alienated any of the Church bookes, ornaments, or goods? if yea, then to whom? and vpon what cauſe? and in whoſe poſſeſſion are
<pb facs="tcp:25480:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
they? and whether hath any Churchwarden or Sworneman at any time concealed any diſorder, crime, or fame of any crime, and not preſented the ſame to be reformed?</p>
            <p n="53">53 Whether for the retayning of the circuite, and limits of your Pariſh doe your Parſon, Vicar, or Curate, Churchwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens, and certaine of the ſubſtantiall men of your Pariſh in the dayes of perambulation, commonly called the Rogation weeke, walke and compaſſe the accuſtomed bounds of your Pariſh? and whether in the ſaid perambulation doth the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter vſe any other right or ceremonie, then to ſay or ſing to the praiſe of God ſome Pſalme of <hi>Dauid</hi> of thankeſgiuing, as the hundred and third, or hundred and fourth Pſalmes, with the Lettanie and prayers following, or reading ſome part of holy Scripture or homely, and without carrying of Banners or handbels, or ſuch like Popiſh obſeruations?</p>
            <p n="54">54 Whether are there any perſons in your Pariſh which doe not diligently reſort to your Pariſh Church, or Chappell accuſtomed, euery Sunday and Holiday according to the ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute? what are their names, who doe not ſo reſort? when haue they ſo beene abſent? and whether doth your Miniſter admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh the Churchwardens openly in the Church after the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Leſſon at morning and euening prayer, to looke to their charge in that behalfe?</p>
            <p n="55">55 What Recuſant Papiſts are there in your Pariſhes? preſent their names, qualities, and conditions, how long haue they abſtained from diuine Seruice or from the Communion: or doe any of them keepe any ornaments of ſuperſtition vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>defaced.</p>
            <p n="56">56 Whether any in your Pariſh (who heretofore being Popiſh Recuſants, haue reformed themſelues) doe ſtill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine and abide in the ſame conformity, and is there a booke prouided in your Pariſh, to regiſter the names of all ſuch Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſants, who ſo conforme and ſubmit themſelues according to the Statute of 35. <hi>Eliz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="57">57 Whether haue you a terrier of all the gleabelands, me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes, gardens, orchards, houſes, ſtockes, implements, tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and portions of tythes (whether within your Pariſh or
<pb facs="tcp:25480:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
without) belonging to your Parſonage or Vicaridge, taken by the view of honeſt men in your Pariſh: and whether the ſame terrier be laide vp in the Biſhops Regiſtrie? and in whoſe hands are any of them now: and if you haue no terrier already made in parchment, you the Churchwardens &amp; Side<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men together with your Parſon or Vicar, or in his abſence with your Miniſter, are to make diligent inquirie and preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the premiſſes, and to make, ſubſcribe, and ſigne a ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rier as aforeſaid.</p>
            <p n="58">58 Whether doth your Miniſter vpon Wedneſdayes and Fridayes, not being Holydayes, reade in your Church or Chappell publiquely the Letany, and other prayers appointed in the booke of Common prayer for thoſe dayes: and whether doth hee read the Commination againſt ſinners, in ſuch order and forme as it is there alſo preſcribed.</p>
            <p n="59">59 Whether doth your Miniſter vpon ſome Sundayes or Holidayes in the after noone before diuine ſeruice, reade ouer once euery yeare all the Canons Eccleſiaſticall, publiſhed by his Maieſties authority <hi>Anno</hi> 1603. publiquely in your Church or Chappell where hee ſerueth, diuiding the ſame in ſuch ſort, as that the one halfe may be read one day, and the other another day.</p>
            <p n="60">60 Whether doth your Miniſter refuſe or delay to chriſten any childe brought to be chriſtned vpon Sundayes and Holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayes, according to the booke of Common prayer: or being informed of his weakeneſſe, or danger of death, doth refuſe to goe to the place where the ſaid Infant remaineth to baptize it.</p>
            <p n="61">61 Whether hath there beene ſince the laſt Viſitation or before, which is not preſented, any contention, brawling, or fighting in your Church, or Churchyard, betwixt any of the Pariſhioners touching the placing or diſplacing of any in any ſeat or Pew in the Church, or touching any other cauſe? and whether hath there beene any Pew builded, or alteration made ſince the foreſaid time in any your Churches, without the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe leaue of the Ordinary of the Dioceſſe, and by whom hath the ſame beene done?</p>
            <p n="62">62 Whether are there any Inne-keepers, Alewiues, or
<pb facs="tcp:25480:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Victualers in your Pariſh, that ſuffer any perſon to eate, drink, or play at Dice, Cards, Tables, Bowles, or ſuch like games in their houſes in the time of Common prayer, or Sermon on Sundayes or Holydayes: whether any Butchers or others doe ſell meate or other things in the time of Common prayer, preaching, or reading of Homilies.</p>
            <p n="63">63 Whether hath any perſon cut downe any tree or trees growing in your Churchyard, to the hurt or preiudice of the Church: and to what vſe was it conuerted as you know, or credibly and publiquely haue heard.</p>
            <p n="64">64 Whether hath your Miniſter or any other Miniſter baptized any childe in your Pariſh, without vſing the ſigne of the Croſſe at the baptiſme thereof: or ſolemnized marriage without vſing the Ring therein according to the book of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon prayer.</p>
            <p n="65">65 Whether is all due reuerence vſed in time of diuine ſeruice, and of euery part thereof, according to the 18. Canon, and whether there be any in your Pariſh that vſe any vnreue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent ſpeeches or ieſtures againſt Miniſters, and in contempt of their calling and function.</p>
            <p n="66">66 Whether any Apparitor or other perſon hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded or ſmothered for reward or fauour, any cauſe or mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of office belonging to the Eccleſiaſticall Court: if yea, then doe you declare the ſame, and what money or reward hee had for the ſame.</p>
            <p n="67">67 And generally whether doe you know of any of the Lawes Eccleſiaſticall violated or broken, or any Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call matters worthy of redreſſe: and if you doe, then you are to preſent the ſame, and in all your preſentments as neere as poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible you may, you are to note the yeare, time, and place of eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry offence committed.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:25480:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:25480:8"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
